E.J. Hale Papers
E.J. Hale Papers
1815 1963
00300
Hale, E.J. (Edward Joseph) 1839-1922
2.0 linear feet
approximately 550 items
Simmons University Library Archives
Edward Joseph Hale was editor of the Fayetteville (N.C.) Observer; Confederate officer; United States consul in Manchester, England, 1885-1889; and United States envoy to Costa Rica, 1913-1916. Papers include E.J. Hale's correspondence, letterbooks, and other items relating to his diplomatic posts; his interest in canal projects at the Isthmus (a small amount), in England, and in North Carolina; state and national politics; and family business matters. The collection includes official and personal correspondence with Woodrow Wilson and correspondence of Hale's sons, Thomas Hill Hale and Frederick Toomer Hale, in Fayetteville, N.C. and Santa Cruz, Calif., concerning family business and the Depression, 1928-1936.
Restrictions to Access
No restrictions. Open for research.
Acquisitions Information
Received from E.J. Hale of Fayetteville, N.C. in 1936; from Lucy Seawell Costen of Gatesville, N.C., in 1966; from Charles B. Overman of Falls Church, Va., in May 1968.
Biographical Information
Edward Joseph Hale, son of Edward Jones Hale and Sarah Jane Walker, was graduated from the University of North Carolina in 1860 as valedictorian. He worked briefly for his father, who was founding editor of the FayettevilleObserver, before enlisting in the Confederate Army. He achieved the rank of major in the Confederate army and remained in service until his surrender with Lane's Brigade at Appomattox. Because of the Observer's support of the Confederacy, Sherman had destroyed its printing presses, which put a temporary end to the enterprise. After the war, Hale entered a mercantile house in New York, where he eventually became a partner. He moved back to North Carolina in 1875 and, in 1882, reestablished the Fayetteville Observer.
Hale was a delegate to the National Democratic Convention in 1884 for which he drafted a tariff plank for its platform. The following year, he was appointed to the position of consul to Manchester, England, a key post because of extensive cotton trade between the South and the manufacturing interests in that city. After his consulship, Hale became the confidential financial agent of the North England Trust Company and was sent to India to investigate the indigo industry and make investments. From 1890 to 1891, he lived in New York as commissioner of the Manchester Ship Canal in North America.
Hale returned to North Carolina in 1892 and resulmed the editorship of the Observer and his position in state politics. In 1894, he was again a member of the North Carolina Democratic Convention, drawing up the National part of the State Platform. He served again in 1896, 1900, 1904 and 1906.
Scope and Content
The collection includes correspondence and other papers of E.J. Hale and Hale family members. Included is official and personal correspondence with Woodrow Wilson and with Hale's sons, Thomas Hill Hale and Frederick Toomer Hale, concerning family business and the Depression, 1928-1936. Much of the correspondence while Hale was consul to England relates to immigration to the United States, the Manchester Ship Canal, the indigo industry of India, the 1916coup d'etat in Mexico, and trade laws. Other papers include special passports and certificates from his consul position, recommendations and endorsements, speeches and articles from both abroad and in North Carolina, newspaper clippings, and some biographical information.
Collection Arrangment
Arranged into Four Series:
Correspondence, 1846-1936
Consul material, 1884-1916
Other papers, 1880-1936
Photographs, 1890-1900
Subject Headings
The following terms from Library of Congress Subject Headings suggest topics, persons, geography, etc. interspersed through the entire collection; the terms do not usually represent discrete and easily identifiable portions of the collection--such as folders or items.
Clicking on a subject heading below will take you into the University Library's online catalog.
Canals England History; Canals North Carolina History; Costa Rica Foreign relatinos United Statesd; Depressinos 1929 United Statesd; Diplomatic and consular service American; Diplomats United Statesd Biography; England Foreign relatinos United Statesd; Family North Carolina Social Life and customs; Hale, E.J. (Edward Joseph) 1839-1922; Hale, Frederick Toomer; Hale, Thomas Hill; North Carolina Politics and government 1865-1950; Panama Canal (Panama) History; United States Foreign relations Costa Rica; United States Foreign relations England; United States Politics and government 1865-1933; Wilson, Woodrow 1856-1924
Items Separated
Items separated included photographs (P-300/1-4)
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Correspondence, 1846-1936; About 310 items.
  Scope and content:
  Correspondence in both letterbook form and loose letters, chiefly 1885-1915. After 1920, correspondence is with E.J. Hale's two sons, Frederick Toomer Hale and Thomas Hill Hale, on family business matters and the Great Depression. Also included is correspondence in 1922 on Hale's death and estate.
  Arrangement:
  Chronological
  - Letterbooks, 1877-1889; 10 items
    Letters containing the correspondence of E.J. Hale mainly while he was consul at Manchester, England.
    - Volume 1: 299 pp. Letterbook, 1877-1880 (Folder 1)
    - Volume 2: 482 pp. Letterbook, 1885-1887 (Folder 2)
    - Volume 3: 248 pp. Letterbook, 1885-1887 (Folder 3)
    - Volume 4: 300 pp. Record book of visitors to the United States Consulate in Manchester., 1886-1889 (Folder 4)
    - Volume 5: 492 pp. Letterbook, 1887-1889 (Folder 5)
    - Volume 6: 499 pp. Letterbook, 1888 (Folder 6)
    - Volume 7: 500 pp. Letterbook, 1888-1889 (Folder 7)
    - Volume 8: 493 pp. Letterbook, 1888-1889 (Folder 8)
    - Volume 9: 486 pp. Letterbook, 1888-1889 (Folder 9)
    - Volume 10: 305 pp. Letterbook, 1891 (Folder 10)
  - Loose Letters, 1847-1936; 300 items
    Correspondence primarily during Hale's years as consul. Most letters discuss international affairs.
    - 1847-1879 (Folder 11)
    - 1880-1888 (Folder 12)
    - 1889 (Folder 13)
    - 1890-1894 (Folder 14)
    - 1895-1899 (Folder 15)
    - 1900-1904 (Folder 16)
    - 1905-1909 (Folder 17)
    - 1910-1912 (Folder 18)
    - 1913 (Folder 19)
    - 1914 (Folder 20)
    - 1915 (Folder 21)
    - 1916 (Folder 22)
    - 1917 (Folder 23)
    - 1920-1924 (Folder 24)
    - 1925-1933 (Folder 25)
    - 1934-1935 and undated (Folder 26)
- Consul material, 1884-1916; About 90 items.
  Primarily statements of support, an application, passports, and clearances for the Manchester consul position, with an additional folder of information on Costa Rica.
  Topical
  - Application for Manchester Consul Position (Folder 27)
  - Statements of Support, American (Folder 28)
  - Statements of Support, British (Folder 29)
  - Financial and legal material, Britain and India (Folder 30)
  - Costa Rica (Folder 31)
- Other papers, 1880-1936; About 150 items.
  Clippings, invitations, and speeches from Hale's career as consul in both England and Costa Rica; speeches and information on projects in North Carolina; and some biographical information.
  - Biographical material (Folder 32)
  - Biographical material on Mrs. Spier Whitaker (Folder 33)
  - Camp Fear River Improvements (Folder 34)
  - Clippings (Folder 35-37)
  - Financial and legal materials (Folder 38)
  - Invitations and other papers (Folder 39)
  - Speeches and writings (Folder 40-41)
- Photographs, 1890-1900; 4 items.
  - Photographs of E.J. Hale, Ca.1900 (Folder P-300/1-3)
  - Photograph of Mrs. E.J. Hale, 1890 (Folder P-300/4)